<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glass discovering to all people what image they bear by which the true Jew is known from the false, and the Christian in nature from him that is so in name only ... : with directions for such as live in error, how they may leave their error, how they may leave their error ... : with a few words  to informers who make it their work to inform against their neighbours for meeting together peaceably in the fear of the Lord ... / by a follower of Him, Edward Bourne.</title>
            <author>Bourne, Edward, d. 1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28894</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28496</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10604099</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10604099</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45394</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28894)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45394)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1398:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glass discovering to all people what image they bear by which the true Jew is known from the false, and the Christian in nature from him that is so in name only ... : with directions for such as live in error, how they may leave their error, how they may leave their error ... : with a few words  to informers who make it their work to inform against their neighbours for meeting together peaceably in the fear of the Lord ... / by a follower of Him, Edward Bourne.</title>
                  <author>Bourne, Edward, d. 1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>2671 [i.e. 1671]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45394:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45394:1"/>
            <p>A Looking-Glaſs Diſcovering to all People what IMAGE they BEAR.</p>
            <list>
               <item>By which the True Jew is known from the falſe, and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in nature, from him that is ſo in name only.</item>
               <item>Likewiſe all people in ſome meaſure may know what ſpirit they are of; and whether they are the Children of God, or of the Devil.</item>
               <item>With directions for ſuch as live in Error, how they may leave their Error, and know the Truth which leads out of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, by which People are made free from ſin, which they run into, and live in, by following the ſpirit of Error.</item>
               <item>With a few words to Informers, who make it their work to Inform againſt their Neighbours, for meeting together peaceably in the fear of the Lord, to Worſhip him, as he requires.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By a Follower of him, who ſaith, <hi>if you continue in my Word, then are you my Diſciples indeed, And ye ſhall know the Truth, and the Truth ſhall make you free, John</hi> 8.31, 32.</p>
            <p>Edward Bourne.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1671.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45394:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45394:2"/>
            <head>A Looking-Glaſs FOR All People to See Themſelves, whether they <hi>be</hi> what they ought to <hi>be,</hi> and <hi>do</hi> as they ought to <hi>do,</hi> or otherwiſe.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ALthough much hath been Written, and Spoken, to turn Peoples minds, to the <hi>Light of Chriſt in them;</hi> to the end that all may do what they ought, in all things, and be what they ought towards God; yet but few have received the Report thereof, though by obeying this <hi>Light,</hi> which is that which leads to keep a Conſcience void of offence towards God and Men, true happineſs is attained unto; and contrariwiſe the neglect hereof, is the cauſe of Peoples ruin, and Eternal Miſery. But notwitſtanding, whether People will hear or forbear, I know none on whom ſuch a Work as this is laid, by the Lord God, can neglect the ſame, but we muſt be Tranſgreſſors our ſelves in this reſpect. And therefore to keep my Conſcience pure towards God, I thus proceed.</p>
               <p>You that live in ſin, you know you ſhould not live ſo, and that which gives you this knowledg, is the Grace of God, which hath appeared unto you, by which, as in a Glaſs, you may ſee your ſelves; by which the Drunkard,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12.</note> ſees he ſhould not be Drunk; and the Lyer, he ſhould not lie; and the Envious Man, he ſhould not live in Envy; and he that Perſecutes his Neighbour, whoſe Works are better then his, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45394:3"/>for that cauſe, all theſe are doing what they ſhould not do, as they themſelves (many of them) in their Prayers to God do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs. And theſe, though they do that which they know they ſhould not do, and leave undone, that which they know they ſhould not leave undone, yet would they have the Lord to have Mercy on them; although their daily practice is thus to Tranſgreſs. They acknowledge they have Tranſgreſſed againſt Gods Holy Law, and too much followed the Devices and deſires of their own hearts, &amp;c. And this is their manner from the beginning of the year, to the end thereof: But (Mark) you that are ſuch, can you believe that God will ſhew Mercy to you, onely on this your Confeſſion? Are you ſo fooliſh, and unwiſe, as ſo to believe? If you do, certainly you will find it otherwiſe in the end: Then your folly will appear, though at the preſent you may account your ſelves wiſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and them fooliſh who are truely wiſe: But I muſt tell you, to be truely wiſe, is to fear the Lord, and to keep his Commandments, though you may not account it ſo.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Object. <hi>But ſome may ſay, What are the Commandments, of God that we are to keep?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe, Thou ſhalt love the Lord God with all thy heart,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deu.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Luke,</hi> 10.27, 28.</note> and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou ſeeſt by the grace of God that hath appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thee, thou oughteſt to do it, and it will be thy Tranſgreſſion to neglect the ſame; therefore do not deceive your ſelves with ſuch a perſwaſion any longer, if you do you will ſhew much folly, and indiſcretion therein, for God will not be mocked with ſuch lip Service. This I am bold in the fear of God to aſſure you of, you may draw neer him with your Lip's, but your Hearts are far from him, whilſt it is onely thus; You muſt not onely confeſs your faults to God, but muſt alſo forſake them, if Mercy with him you would find: And this is the Word of God unto you. Let the Wicked Man forſake his way, and the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man his thoughts, and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have Mercy upon him, and to our God, for he will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly Pardon him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45394:3"/>
                  <p>You pray that God would deliver you from all Envy, and Malice, and from all uncharitableneſs, and from all the works of the Devil: But if you were delivered from all theſe abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, happy would you be; then God who delivereth his People from all theſe would be your God. But your Teachers many of them are Envious themſelves; and uncharitable them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp;c. Therefore it may be you are the more imboldened to commit all theſe Abominations: But if you, and your Teachers, would take heed to the Grace of God that bringeth Salvation, that thereby you may be guided, you would know the Lord God to be your Teacher, who teacheth his People to profit; and ſo be delivered from all theſe Abominations, and all the works of the Devil, and then we ſhould not ſuffer by you as we do; for the Truth being your Guide, and Teacher, you will give us the ſame liberty to Worſhip God, that you would have your ſelves, and ſo do as you would be done by in this, and in all things; and ſo hereby you will do what you ought to do, and be what you ought to be towards God; and not before, viz. you cannot do, nor be, as you ought till you be guided by the Truth, which leads to meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and lowlyneſs, by which God will direct you in all your wayes; then ſhall you be far from oppreſſion, and violence, and ſpoil will be (as it may be ſaid) baniſhed from your Habitations, that ſpirit which leads to unrighteouſneſs not being harkened unto, but the Voice of the Lord God obeyed, and his Councel ſtood in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Object. <hi>But ſome may ſay, you direct us</hi> to the Light within, <hi>that by taking heed unto it, we may forſake that which God requires us to forſake, and do what we ought to do, that ſo we may be what we ought to be towards him. You alſo will acknowledge that that which m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es to unrighteouſneſs, and unholineſs, is within; And ſeeing that it is ſo, that both theſe are within, how ſhall they be known, and diſtinguiſhed the one, from the other? How ſhall that be rejected and forſaken, that ought ſo to be? And that followed and obeyed, that ought to be followed and obeyed? Eſpecially becauſe that Principle
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45394:4"/>which leads to unrighteouſneſs, ſometimes appeares like that which moves unto Righteouſneſs. How ſhall we diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the one, and the other, and follow that which we ought to follow, and avoid the contrary, in ſuch a difficult caſe as this? &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis true, that both theſe are within, The heart of Man is deceitful, and deſperately wicked, &amp;c. as the Scriptures teſtifies: But the Lord by his Light in the heart diſcovers this to his Creature which he hath made, and is the Work of his Hands, and by it he being therein hearkened unto, and obeyed, helps the Creature from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into the Snare which the Enemy of the Soul would (by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticing) draw him into, and ſo though there is that <hi>within People</hi> that would Intice, and lead them into Sin; yet is there alſo that within which ſhews the Creature the Evil thereof, and doth diſcover from whence it doth proceed, and being harkened unto, as it ought, and obeyed, doth preſerve the Creature thereby out of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; and ſo hereby God doth deliver his Creature (Man) whom he hath formed, out of the ſnares of the Devil, who goeth about like a roaring <hi>Lion,</hi> ſeeking whom he may devour: And though he doth appear like an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> as he is mentioned in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. yet by the True <hi>Light</hi> he is diſcovered, which <hi>Light</hi> leadeth to fear the Lord, and do his will, and his ſnares are avoided, that <hi>Light</hi> and Truth being followed, and obeyed, which makes a diſcovery of him; and ſo hereby the Lord preſerves his Creature, which he hath made by his own mighty Power, to his own Praiſe, and the Creatures joy and Comfort. Glory be given to God on high forever.</p>
                  <p>And ſo it is by a dilligent taking heed to that which is pure of God within, that this comes to be known, and witneſſed, and tis by this the Soul comes to live, which was dead; hereby the quickening Power of God is known, which quickens, and makes alive to him, they who are dead to him by reaſon of their Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, and Sins, by inclining their Ears, and hearkening dilligently to that which is <hi>pure of God in themſelves, that they may be guided thereby only;</hi> and ſo hereby ſuch are led to repent, and Sin no more; and ſo becomes Followers of Chriſt, who ſaid to the Woman taken
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45394:4"/>in Adultery, Sin no more, &amp;c. And ſo that bleſſed ſtate comes to be known, which is without Sin, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Object. <hi>But ſome may ſay this is ſtrange Doctrine, if we mean a ſtate without Sin in this World; what can People be freed from their Sins, while they be on this ſide the Grave? do not tell us ſo, our Teachers have told us, that ſuch a ſtate is not to be expected while we are in this World: 'Tis true we ought not to Sin but to ſtrive againſt it, but we ſhall never be delivered from it while we are here; it is Erronious thus to hold, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If People do not know a freedom from Sin here in this World: Where then? What ground is there for them to believe That they ſhall attain to ſuch a ſtate hereafter? Seeing it is ſaid there is no Repentance in the Grave; and as Death leaves, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment finds; and no unclean thing can enter the Kingdom of God: If People muſt not be cleanſed here, I would know where they ſhall? 'Tis groſs to hold that there is a <hi>Purgatory</hi> after Death for Peoples Soules to depart into, when they ſhall leave this World where their Sins ſhall be purged away; and if there be no ſuch Place, as I ſuppoſe you will not grant there is (except you are Popiſhly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) then let not ſuch plead for a never being made free from Sin while they are here; if ye do well conſider it, will it not be beſt for you to grant that there is a <hi>Purgatory,</hi> where ſin is to be purged away afterwards, if you would live in Sin Term of Life? But Sin is to be Purged away here, you muſt know Chriſt to free you from your Sins while you are here, elſe Wo will be to you, if you put it off till hereafter.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt came to ſave his People from their Sins and to deſtroy the works of the Devil, which is Sin:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21.</note> And who doth not know this Work wrought in them by Chriſt, they cannot ſo properly call him their Saviour; For how is he a Saviour to ſuch who are not ſaved by him, from their Sins? Chriſt taught Perfection here; the Apoſtles and Saints knew a being made free from Sin, while they were in this World; and their Labour, and Work, was that they might preſent every Man Perfect in Chriſt Jeſus. See <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.28.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45394:5"/>
                  <p>Therefore ſuch as Teach and hold otherwiſe are contrary to Chriſt, and contrary to his Miniſters, then judge whoſe Miniſters they be, for the Miniſters of Chriſt they cannot be ſaid to be; who teach contrary to him; and therefore are they to be turned away from, and not to be believed.</p>
                  <p>So while that Spirit Rules in the Heart, which leads to Sin, there is not room for Truth, but Sin is lived in, the Spirit of Truth not being obeyed, which frees from Sin; and ſo while it is thus, ſuch cannot be ſaid to be the Servants of Righteouſneſs, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.20. And ſo while People follow ſuch, they give their Money for that which is not Bread; and their Labour for that which ſatisfieth nor, ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.2. Therefore turn your minds to the Light of Chriſt in you, that you may know the Lord to be your Teacher; who teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his People to profit; ſo will you be taught of him, and in Righteouſneſs will you be eſtabliſhed; ſo hereby you will know him your Teacher, who ſaith, Whoſoever will, let him take the Water of Life freely, ſee <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17.</p>
                  <p>So here I give you a mark, whereby you ſhall know the Miniſters of Chriſt, from others, the Miniſters of Chriſt they gave freely as they have freely received, according to the Commandment of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.8. The Miniſters of Antichriſt preach for Hire, and filthy lucre, and ſeek for their gain from their Quarters, like the falſe Prophets, and like thoſe mentioned in the Scriptures, prepare war againſt them that puts not into their Mouthes. <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.5. And whether <hi>William Ley,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Nicholaſs Pariſh</hi> in <hi>Worceſter,</hi> did not like them, for his <hi>Belly,</hi> on the account of his <hi>Eaſter</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konings (as he calls it) <hi>Caſt</hi> into, and <hi>Keep Robert Smith,</hi> and <hi>Edward Bourne</hi> of that <hi>Pariſh</hi> in <hi>Priſon;</hi> And would not make it appear to them it was his Right, according to the <hi>Law of God;</hi> which he ought to have done; weigh theſe things with the Truth in your ſelves, which weighs and meaſures things aright, and give judgment herein accordingly: The Ballance of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you will know, which weighs things aright; here you will know that within, which the outward was a Figure of; and conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be the Miniſters of Chriſt, that love to be called <hi>Maſter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.6, 7.</note> and love <hi>Salutations in the Markets, and the Chiefeſt Places in the Aſſemblies, and the uppermoſt Rooms at Feaſts,</hi> ſeeing Chriſt forbad it, and cryed wo to ſuch?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45394:5"/>and whether ſuch as theſe do not run and the Lord never ſent them, who are ſo contrary to the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs? They would have money for Bread, and Wine, at <hi>Eaſter</hi> (ſo called) which they call the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> although the People never receive it: But whether it be Equal and Juſt in them to deſire Money from People for nought? Let they that ſhall read this conſider; did not the Apoſtle and Servant of the Lord ſay, That they did not eat any Mans Bread for nought; And they would not make the Goſpel chargable, &amp;c? I would know wherein theſe are followers of thoſe who would have others to follow them, as they followed Chriſt; For my part I do not know wherein in one particular; But they may be ſaid to be followers of them who were contrary to Chriſt Jeſus in many particulars: They take and give that which they call the <hi>Lords Supper before and after Dinner;</hi> and ſo do contrary to the Inſtitution therein; For Chriſt took the <hi>Cup after Supper</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed it,</hi> and <hi>gave</hi> to his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> as you may ſee, <hi>Luke</hi> 22 20. And though we cannot touch, nor taſte, nor handle with them, in thoſe things which are to periſh in the uſing, after the Doctrines and Traditions of Men; yet the <hi>Supper of the Lord</hi> we own, and do witneſs the Subſtance of what was figured forth thereby, Glory be given to him who is Holy, and lives for evermore.</p>
                  <p>Theſe and their followers who are taught by them ſay; 'tis true we ought not to Sin; but to ſtrive againſt it: But we ſhall never be delivered from Sin, while we are in this Life, &amp;c. Now what hopes is there for People to overcome the Enemy of their Souls, if the caſe ſtands thus? If They do not follow ſuch Teachers, they can be but the Devils Captives; and if they do ſo, they muſt ſo continue it ſeems; For he that lives in Sin ſerves the Devil, and ſo is his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; For ſo they muſt continue it ſeems, while they be here, and that is ſo long as they can be followed; then ſure they cannot be the ſervants of Righteouſneſs, whilſt they obey the ſpirit of Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>The promiſe of that life that is Eternal is to him that overcomes, and not to him that doth not. He that is made <hi>a Conqueror;</hi> and <hi>more through Chriſt,</hi> he overcomes: But how will any prevail while they follow ſuch as ſay it can never be in this Life? Was it not in this Life the Apoſtles were made more then Conquerours through Chriſt? This I would know. ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45394:6"/>
                  <p>You that follow ſuch Teachers, did not your god-fathers, and god-mothers (ſo called) promiſe, and vow, for you in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> that when you came to Age, you ſhould forſake the Devil, and all his Works, &amp;c? And what do your Teachers tell you now the contrary? ſaying; It can never be in this Life, but you muſt alwayes live in Sin till you come to your Graves. Now Sin is the Work of the Devil, and if People muſt always, when they be here, live in Sin; then, How can it be ſaid, it being ſo, that they have forſaken the Devil and all his Works? Conſider what confuſion is here; and be awakened unto Righteouſneſs, that fruit may be brought forth by you unto God, who will not be mocked with your Lip-ſervice, in calling Chriſt Lord, and yet doing contrary to what he Commands; who ſaid to his Diſciples, Be Perfect as your Father which is in Heaven is Perfect: So to draw neer to God with your Lips will not ſerve your turn, or make you acceptable unto him: But you muſt draw neer with your Hearts alſo, and do well, and as you ought, or elſe all your good ſayings will be in vain, and to no purpoſe. The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaid, So <hi>ſay,</hi> and So <hi>do,</hi> ſee <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.12. And Chriſt ſaith, Not every one that ſaith unto me Lord, Lord, that ſhall enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven: But he that doth the will of my Father, &amp;c. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſee to it, you that ſhall come to read theſe lines. I charge you in the preſence of the Lord, that you be found doing his Holy Will, that you may bring forth fruit unto him; leſt he cut you down as fruitleſs Trees, and caſt ye into the fire.</p>
                  <p>So theſe things before mentioned being conſidered, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that it is not erronious to hold, that a freedom from Sin is to be attained unto here in this Life; but that it is erronious, and Deviliſh, to Teach, and Hold, the contrary. And if it be erronious to hold that we ſhould live without Sin, then it was erronious in our god-fathers, and god-mothers, (ſo called) to promiſe, and vow, on our behalfs, that when we came to Age, we ſhould forſake the Devil, and all his Works, &amp;c. Which if we do, certainly we muſt ceaſe from Sin, and not live any longer therein; for while Sin is lived in, the Devil and all his Works cannot be ſaid to be forſaken; becauſe Sin is the Work of the Devil, which Chriſt came to deſtroy; and ſo it is thoſe who can truely and properly call Chriſt their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who witneſſeth that he hath ſaved them from their Sins, which is the cauſe of the wrath, and diſpleaſure of the Almighty; ſo the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45394:6"/>true Followers of Chriſt, the true Diſciples of Chriſt, they know and can declare it to the praiſe and honour of the moſt high God; that it is Jeſus who hath ſaved them from the wrath to come, ſee 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10.</p>
                  <p>So who would be, as they ought to be, and do as they ought to do, muſt abſtain from every thing, which the holy Light of Chriſt in them makes appear in them to be evil, and follow this good and holy Light only, that by it they may be led into all truth, by which the God of truth is known, and come to, which who comes to, muſt believe that God is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him, and they who do refuſe to be guided by the Light of Jeſus Chriſt in them, which is that which God hath appointed all People to be guided by; it is them that do otherwiſe then they ought to do, and be not what God requires them to be; ſuch were thoſe the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſpake of, forgetful hearers of the Word, who neglected to do it,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.23, 24.</note> whom he compared to a natural man, who beholds his face in a Glaſs, and ſtraitway forgets what manner of man he is; ſo what is the difference between ſuch as refuſe to hear the voice of truth, that they may do it, and thoſe who are forgetful hearers, who are negligent in doing according to the Word, that they have heard? this I ſhall leave to ſuch as ſhall read theſe lines, to give righteous judgment therein.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now it is to be conſidered, what it is to be a True <hi>Jew.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ABraham</hi> was a true <hi>Jew,</hi> and all his Poſterity, they were and are called <hi>Jewes;</hi> but all were not true <hi>Jewes,</hi> nor are ſo, who came of the Loyns of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but thoſe who were, and are, guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Spirit of Truth, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, ſuch are the Children of the Promiſe, who are accounted for the ſeed of <hi>Abraham; Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> he kept the Commandments of the Lord, and they are the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45394:7"/>true <hi>Jewes,</hi> who do like <hi>Abraham</hi> herein; the Lord ſaid of him, hat he will command his Children, and his Houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do juſtice and judgment, that the Lord may bring upon <hi>Abraham,</hi> that which he hath ſpoken of him, ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. he ſaid they ſhall keep the Way of the Lord, &amp;c. Now what is it to keep the Way of the Lord, but to be led and guided by the Spirit of the Lord, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was? and they who are led by this; 'Tis they I do affirm to be the true <hi>Jewes,</hi> and not others, viz. Not ſuch as walk contrary to it, and do rebel againſt it; the Apoſtle ſaid, He is not a <hi>Jew,</hi> who is one outward; neither is that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, that is outward in the fleſh; but he is a <hi>Jew</hi> which is one inward and Circumciſion is that of the Heart, in the Spirit, and not in the Letter, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29. Now they who are led by the Spirit of God, at this time, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was led by the Spirit of God then, to the Circumciſion that was out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the fleſh, ſo are ſuch now led to the Circumciſion within, of which the outward was a Figure; So that which God requires of People, is that they do as he makes manifeſt unto them, they ought by the meaſure of his own Spirit which he have given them to profit withall, and leads them unto by his Spirit; Now if they do what the Servants of God did, as is Recorded in the Scriptures, if they be not led thereunto, as they were by his holy Spirit; he may ſay unto them who hath required this at your hands? This is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter which Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples he would ſend, which ſhould lead them into all truth; and bleſſed are they who do walk accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Rule, viz. Who are led and guided, by the holy Spirit of the Lord God in what they do, and not they who do gainſay and reſiſt it: See what became of <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram, Corah's</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who gainſaid this holy Spirit; they were ſwallowed up of the Earth: <hi>Moſes</hi> who was guided by the Spirit of the Lord God, prayed the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to depart from the Tents of thoſe wicked Men, and to touch nothing that was theirs, leſt they ſhould be conſumed in all their Sins.</p>
               <p>Now let they who ſhall read theſe lines conſider, whether there be not too great a Multitude, that do reſiſt this holy Spirit now, not regarding how God did puniſh ſuch before, though theſe things
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45394:7"/>were written for their admonition, there are too many whoſe Sin are like <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Gomorab,</hi> whom God over threw: And though this ſore judgment was written, with many more, that befel the diſobedient, and rebellious, that they who ſhould come after them, ſhould not do as they did; yet what ſmall regard do they take of the ſame? Well, though the Lord God be ſlow to wrath, and of great kindneſs, and do ſuffer long, and bear long; yet his long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering will come to an end, and his great kindneſs will come to an end with ſuch, if they do not turn to him, and amend their wayes, and their doings while his Spirit ſtrives with them, when that ceaſes to ſtrive with them, and the things that belongs to their peace comes to be hid from their Eyes; then they may wiſh they had never been born, when their miſery comes upon them; this was the ſtate of the miſerable <hi>Jewes</hi> after God had long ſtrove with them, over whom Chriſt took up a lamentation; ſee and ſeriouſly conſider, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37. And do not deceive, your ſelves by perſwading your ſelves it ſhall go well with you, though you follow your ſinful Luſts, and Pleaſures, and the imaginations of your own fooliſh Hearts; do you think, you whoſe Mouthes are fuil of Curſing, and Swearing, and Bitterneſs, and live in Drunkeneſs, and Whoredom, and are Envious, and Perſecutors of the Righteous and Juſt, that <hi>Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>m,</hi> whom the Earth ſwallowed up, and the <hi>Sodomites;</hi> whom God overthrew, were greater Sinners; I tell you nay, but except you repent, you ſhall, as Chriſt ſaid likewiſe Periſh.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Object. <hi>But ſome may ſay, Are there any now, that we are to departs from their Tents? And to touch nothing of theirs, leſt we be conſumed in all their Sins; if there be, Who are they? or What be they? That we may beware of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are ſuch now, whoſe <hi>Tents</hi> are to be departed from, or dwellings: They are thoſe, who have ſold themſelves to do wickedly, whoſe life is in Sin, and do make it a ſport to tranſgreſs againſt the Lord, by breaking his holy and Righteous Laws, who ſerve other gods then the Lord God, who made the World, and all things therein, contrary to his holy Command: who follow after Covetouſneſs, contrary to his holy Command, who are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45394:8"/>Murderers, Adulterers, and Swearers;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.3.</note> contrary to his holy Commandments, and are Haters of that which is good, and Perſecutors of the Righteous, contrary to his holy will and appointment, and do not as they would be done unto, and ſo are contrary to Chriſt, who gave this Commandment: Now ſuch as are found in theſe things, and do live in theſe things, and in whatſoever by the <hi>Light</hi> of Chriſt in them, they ſee to be evil, it is they whoſe <hi>Tents</hi> are to be departed from, and nothing of their's is to be touched; none of their Sins muſt People love to live in, leſt they be conſumed in the ſame: Therefore be warned in the fear of the Lord to depart from ſuch, and touch nothing that is their's, do not Sin like them in any of theſe things, leſt you be conſumed therein; So to be a true <hi>Jew,</hi> is to be guided by the Spirit of Truth, us was <hi>Abraham</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> the Father of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And now let it be conſider'd, what it is to be a True <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is ſaid in the holy Scriptures, that all are not <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that are called <hi>Iſrael.</hi> So I ſay, though there are many that are called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> yet there are none of theſe true <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but who are guided by the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaid <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek, and lowly in heart, and you ſhall find reſt unto your Souls.</hi> So 'tis them who are guided by the Spirit of Chriſt, which leads to meekneſs, and lowlineſs of heart, that are the true <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and not thoſe who are biting, and devouring on another, who live in Pride, and High-mindedneſs; Nor thoſe who are fighting one with the other, and Slaying one another, and Perſecuting one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother about Religion, and Church Worſhip; theſe are not the true Chriſtians; theſe are guided by <hi>Cains</hi> Spirit who ſlew his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe his Brothers Works were better them his; Theſe have the Name, but are out of the Nature: They want
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45394:8"/>the Nature of true Chriſtians, and ſo are like them who ſaid, They were <hi>Jews:</hi> But did lye, ſee <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.9.</p>
               <p>The true Chriſtians are guided by Chriſt's Spirit, which leads them to love one another, and their Enemies alſo; and to bleſs ſuch as curſe them, and not to overcome evil with the ſame, but to overcome it with that which is of a contrary Nature to it; namely, that which is good; and not to ſwear at all, but to ſpake the truth (without ſwearing) in obedience to Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith Swear not at all, but their Yea is Yea, and their Nay is Nay, without an Oath, as Chriſt teacheth, ſo they are ſuch, as hear his ſayings, and do them, and ſo differ greatly from them, who call Chriſt Lord, and yet do not the things which he ſaith; and ſo the true Chriſtians are ſubject to Chriſt Jeſus in doing whatſoever he commands them, the Spirit to Chriſt is that which they be led and guided by, that holy Spirit which calls to follow peace, and holineſs with all men, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord, though he be called by the beſt name, and do profeſs never ſo much of Chriſtianity. Thus, in ſhore, I have ſhewed what it is to be a true Chriſtian.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Object. <hi>But it is commonly objected, that things can never be well in Church, or State, which People who are contrary the one to the other in their Worſhip, may have liberty to Worſhip God in their particular manners, every particular ſort of People, viz. The</hi> Papiſts, <hi>The</hi> Epiſcopal <hi>men, Thoſe called</hi> Baptiſts, <hi>and thoſe called</hi> Quakers, &amp;c. <hi>Which muſt all have liberty to follow that which they think beſt; This cannot do well, ſay They: We ſhall never do well, until all are brought to one Uniformity in their Worſhip, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Can you do better herein, then the Apoſtle and Servant of Chriſt Jeſus councelled in ſuch Caſes as theſe? Who ſaid, Let every Man be fully perſwaded in his own Mind in what he doth; For whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin; Now as the <hi>Papiſt</hi> would have liberty to Worſhip God in that Way which he judges beſt, ſo the ſame liberty he would have, muſt he give to another. The
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45394:9"/>
                     <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Man muſt do the ſame, and ſo the reſt: And lay aſide all Forcing, and Compelling, and Perſecuting about theſe things, and who are in the right Way, let them make it appear by their Meekneſs, and Gentleneſs, and Patience, &amp;c. And ſo let them by their ſound Doctrine, and good Converſation, convince them that are contrary minded if they can; ſo long as all theſe are peaceable, and do nothing that tends to the diſturbance of the Common Wealth, nor to the injury of any Perſon, but do onely Worſhip God as they judge they ought: What ſhall Men take on them to judge in ſuch caſes, and to Puniſh in ſuch caſes, if ſuch err in their Worſhip, ſeeing it belongs to God to judge, and Puniſh for the ſame? Now if Men take this upon them, do not they do what they ought not; ſeeing the thing belongs to God, and not to Man to do thus? If any err herein, they ought to be admoniſhed, that they may deſiſt from their error, and cloſe which the Truth, by which they ſee their error. Chriſt ſaid who is to be heard in all things, If thy Brother offend tell him between him and thee, if he hears thee thou haſt gaind thy Brother, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17. if he do not hear, take one or two more with thee; if he do not hear them, then tell the Church; if he do not hear the Church, then let him be as the <hi>Heathen,</hi> or the <hi>Publican;</hi> he doth not ſay, Perſecute him, Burn him for a <hi>Heretick,</hi> but let him be as the <hi>Heathen,</hi> or the <hi>Publican.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Further, Chriſt ſpeaking of falſe Prophets, ſaid, Believe them not; But did not bid his Followers to Perſecute, and Deſtroy them. And further, conſider Chriſt's Parable concerning the Tares, which the Enemy ſowed while Men ſlept, and what the Houſholder ſaid to his Servant thereupon that informed him of the ſame, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30. Which plainly ſhews, that ſuch ſhould be left to God, who err in point of Religion, and Church Worſhip, to be judged by him for the ſame, who is the judge of all the Earth, and will do right.</p>
                  <p>So let all have liberty to Worſhip God as they are perſwaded in their own Minds they ought, and not be barred therefrom, ſo long as they be peaceable, and do nothing that tends to the diſturbance of the Common Wealth, or injury of any Perſon, viz. Whilſt theſe things cannot be juſtly charged upon them, and this is Goſpel
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45394:9"/>liberty; and till this be given, viz. Liberty of Conſcience in things relateing to the Worſhip of God, it cannot be well, in Church nor ſtate. Now if any err herein not willingy, but do it becauſe they judge they ought, and are ſincere herein towards God, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs God will when he ſees it beſt for ſuch, diſcover their error to them, and lead them therefrom, and guide them in the right Way by his own Spirit, which doth not, nor cannot erre; ſo here is no liberty deſired for People to live in drunkenneſs, or in ſtealing from any, or to offer violence to any Perſon, &amp;c. if any do after this manner, let them be reſtrained, and puniſhed, as God by his holy Laws has appointed, which anſwers that of God in all Peoples Conſciences.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here is ſhewed, how People may know what ſpirit they are of; whether they be the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Moſt High God, or the Children of the Devil, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THis muſt be by what is brought forth by them, for by the Fruit is the Tree to be known, whether it be good, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; For a good Tree, ſaith Chriſt, Bringeth forth good Fruit, But an evil Tree evil Fruit, &amp;c. So by what is brought forth may it be known, or judged, of what ſpirit People are, or by what ſpirit they are led, and guided. Now the Children of God are led by his Spirit; alſo the Children of the Devil, are led by the ſpirit of the Devil. The fruits of the Spirit of the Lord are theſe, viz. Love, Joy, Peace, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21.</note> Meekneſs, Temperance, &amp;c. And the fruits of the ſpirit of the Devil, or the Works of the fleſh are theſe, viz. ſwearing upon any occaſion whatſoever, when People know by that of God in their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they ſhould not ſwear at all; Drunkenneſs, Lying, Fornication,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45394:10"/>Envy, Malice, Perſecution, Fraud, Diſſimulation, (Idolatry) or any thing elſe that a Man may ſet up in his Mind, and love more then the Truth; whether it be Covetouſneſs, or whatſoever it be; for all theſe are Idolatry, and all theſe are evil fruits: So who are in theſe things, they cannot be ſaid to pleaſe God, nor to be of God, who is the Author of all good; in this ſaid <hi>John,</hi> The Children of God are manifeſted, and the Children of the Devil; whoſoever is born of God doth not commit Sin, &amp;c. And further, he ſaith, Whoſoever doth not Righteouſneſs is not of God, ſee 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9, 10. &amp;c. Chriſt, ſaid to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were doing the Works of the Devil, (when they ſaid God was their Father) ſaid he, If God was your Father you would love me; becauſe I proceeded and came forth from him; but ſaid he, You are of your Father the Devil, and his Works you will do, who was a Lyer, and a Murderer from the beginning, and abode not in the Truth, &amp;c. Theſe were Betrayers, and Murderers of the Juſt, and holy One, and yet took on them to be the Children of God, calling him their Father, but made it appear that the Devil was their Father, by doing the Works of the Devil, which was to murder, and betray the Righteous; and theſe ſaid, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was their Father, but were far from his Works: So like them, many that are called Chriſtians, that have the name, but are out of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of true Chriſtians, they oppreſs the Righteous, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Righteous, who are the true followers of Chriſt, and pertakers of his Nature, and betrayes, and murders them, and yet would be counted holy and true Chriſtians, when it is quite contrary; for ſuch are altogether, and wholly againſt Chriſt, and ſo are followers of Antichriſt, who oppreſſeth and gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſt, and not the Followers of Chriſt Jeſus; and theſe would be accounted according to holy Church, and Members of holy Church; But whether they be, let that of God in all conſciences judge. So away with theſe, who ſay they are Chriſtians, and would be accounted truely ſo, but are otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>But the true followers of Chriſt Jeſus, have the Teſtimony in themſelves, that they pleaſe God, as <hi>Enoch</hi> had, who walked with God in his Generation. Now theſe falſe Chriſtians that have the name, but are out of the nature of true Chriſtians, they want this Teſtimony, For that of God in their conſciences condemns
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45394:10"/>them for walking contrary to it; for if they did according to it, they would bring forth fruit unto God, which whilſt they diſobey the juſt, by acting contrary to that of God in their conſciences, they are far from, but are heaping up unto themſelves Wrath, againſt the Day of Wrath; ſo though they take upon them to be true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, yet do they want the Teſtimony of Truth in their Conſciences, to aſſure them that it is ſo, as the Apoſtle who was a true follower of Chriſt, and thoſe who are ſuch <hi>have,</hi> who ſaid, We know we are of God, and the whole World lyes in Wickedneſs, and we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, whereby we know him that is true; this is true God, and Eternal Life, ſee <hi>John</hi> 5.6, 20. Which the true Chriſtians know, and are witneſſes of Glory, and Praiſe, and Honour, be given to the moſt high God who is holy, and lives for ever: So by what is brought forth may it be known what ſpirit People are of, or by what ſpirit they are led and gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d; and ſo whoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren they are, whether they are the Children of God, or the Children of the Devil; the Children of God do like him, who is righteous, holy and Juſt; and the Children of the Devil, are like their father the Devil, who was a Lyar, and a Murderer from the beginning, and abode not in the Truth, and ſo like him dwell in darkneſs, and have their habitation there, and not in the Light of the Lord; For how can they dwell in the Light whilſt they are contrary to it, and will not come to it to be guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereby? whoſoever thou art, that ſhall read theſe lines, be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the conſideration thereof, that it may tend to thy good, and not to thy harm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45394:11"/>
               <head>Directions for ſuch as live in Error, how they may leave their Error; and know the Truth, which leads out of Error; by which People are made free from ſin, which they run into and live in, by following the Spirit of Error.</head>
               <p>SO 'tis the ſpirit of error, this ſpirit of the Devil, which too many are guided by, who will not come to that which ſhews them their error, that they may be led therefrom, unto God; You will not come to me ſaid Chriſt to the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> that you might have Life: Now 'tis by following Chriſt, that error is ſeen, and the ſpirit of error ſhunned, and avoided; ſo who are in error, and ſees your error, to that which lets you ſee your error, which is the Light Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightened you withall, do I in the fear of God direct your minds, that by taking dilligent heed unto it, you may be led therefrom, unto God, who is holy, and lives for ever. So hereby you will know Truth, the Spirit of Truth, which makes free, to free you from your Sins, and Chriſt you will witneſs to be the Saviour of your Souls, who ſaves from Sin, and gives power over Sin, and him who is the Author thereof, viz. the Devil, ſo you will be no longer in bondage to the Devil, the Auther of Sin, nor a Slave to your own corruptions; but may to the praiſe of the moſt high God, declare to others what God hath done for your Souls, to your great joy and ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>So who can receive the report herein given of the Truth, and in other Writings that are given forth therefrom, let them; that we may not complain as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> did, who ſaid, Lord, Who hath believed our report, &amp;c. ſee <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.1. And conſider of the ſame, and what Chriſt ſpake by way of compariſon, of that Generation amongſt whom he was, before he ſuffered, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. &amp;c. The Lord give the Reader an underſtanding herein, and a Heart to do accordingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:45394:11"/>
               <head>A few Words to Informers, who make it their Work to inform againſt their Neighbours, for Meeting together peaceably in the Fear of the Lord, to Worſhip him as he requires.</head>
               <p>COnſider what you are doing; do you do the will of God herein? or is it otherwiſe? viz. do you do it becauſe you hate that which is good, and be at enmity againſt thoſe whoſe Works are better then yours are? Conſider if it be your minds, and your purpoſes not to amend, wherein you have need to amend your wayes, and your doings, that you may be what you ought, both in reſpect to God, and all People, doing to all People wherein you have to do with them, as you would be done by your ſelves: I ſay, If the caſe ſtands thus with you; whether your Sin will not be the leſs, if you do nothing to the injury of them, who deſire to Worſhip God according to his holy will, who is a Spirit, and muſt be Worſhipped in the Spirit, and in the Truth; and be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and all People, wherein they ſhall be concerned with them, as they ought, and as God requires them to be. Certainly if you can refrain your ſelves from being injurious to ſuch, your Sin will be the leſs, and you may expect to receive comfort from God in that reſpect, who is juſt and holy, and will reward all according to their Works: You may do well to conſider the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full end of ſome mentioned in the Scriptures, who made it their buſineſs to Inform againſt the Righteous, who fell into the Snares they had laid for the Righteous, as <hi>Hammon,</hi> who informed againſt <hi>Mordecai</hi> the Jew, and thoſe who informed againſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> and take warning thereby, ſee <hi>Eſther</hi> 7.10. &amp;c. and <hi>Daniel</hi> 6.24. Surely, Friends, if you ſhall think to increaſe your Riches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and to be the more proſperous becauſe thereof; certainly you will find it otherwiſe, ſuch doing will not tend to your good,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45394:12"/>but harm; they will bring a Curſe upon you, and not a Bleſſing; For God will ſet himſelf againſt you, for his People's ſakes, who have no helper in the Earth, and plead their Cauſe with you to your great overthrow, and deſtruction, except you repent of ſuch doings before it be to late, and do no more after the ſame manner again; But if you will not take warning, but are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to go on in theſe things, in oppoſition againſt God, and his People; for ſo may your doings be juſtly ſaid to be, then will you find the Lords Power ſtronger then yours, and him greater in might and ſtrength then you all, to ſubdue you, and lay you low, for riſing and lifting your ſelves up againſt his Heritage; and in the mean time, we ſhall with his help bear what we may ſuffer by you with patience, and not reſiſt in a way of hoſtility, but ſtand ſtill to ſee the Salvation of God: So remember you were thus far cautioned, and warned to have a care what you do touching things of this nature.</p>
               <p>And be it known, that we do not Meet in pretence to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, with an intent to Plot, and contrive Inſurrections, for this we deteſt and abhor; but peaceably to exhort; and ſtir up one anothers pure minds unto that which is good, that the Lord may be glorified by us, and we built upon the Foundation that God hath laid in Sion, which is Elect and Pretious, the Rock of Ages, and of Generations, the chief Corner-ſtone, of which Building is Chriſt Jeſus, which none can know, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but by taking heed to that good thing in them, which did never conſent to Sin; but did ever teſtifie againſt it, and reprove and condemn for it, which calls unto all to follow peace and holineſs with all People, without which, whatever People do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, they cannot ſee God.</p>
               <p>And therefore you that are evil Workers, to that in you which lets you ſee the evil of your Wayes, to that take heed, that thereby you may be led therefrom unto God, that your hearts may be purified, and made clean, and you waſhed from your Sins, and from your filthineſs with Chriſt's Blood, that you may appear ſpotleſs before the Throne of God and the Lamb, that his Name may be in your foreheads, and you bleſſed with ſeeing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45394:12"/>and living in his preſence, where there is joy unſpeakable and glorious.</p>
               <p>Thus have I finiſhed this Work, which, who can receive it let them; and if they receive any profit thereby, let them give Glory to God: Now whether any ſhall hear, or forbear to hear it, I am ſatisfied that I have done my Duty herein. To God alone be all Honour and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Given, even as it is due from me, and all his everywhere, for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Worceſter</hi> Cit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Priſon, where I have long ſuffered Impriſonment for Righteouſneſs ſake, ſometimes with many of my dear Friends, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alone; and yet I am not alone, for the mighty God is with me, to uphold me in my Sufferings; who makes things eaſie, which otherwiſe would be hard.
<date>The 10th of the 11th Moneth, 1670.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>E. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:45394:13"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>WOuld God that all that do account themſelves the Miniſters of Chriſt, were really ſo; then would they not be like the falſe Prophets, mention'd in the Scriptures, as many of them be; who did preach for Hire, and divine for Money, and ſought for their Gain from their Quarters, and prepar'd War againſt them that put not into their Mouthes, <hi>Micah</hi> 3.5. nor like them that Chriſt cry'd Wo againſt, Who loved to be call'd of men Maſters, and lov'd the chiefeſt Places in the Aſſemblies, &amp;c. ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. Neither would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be like the falſe Teachers, mention'd by the Apoſtle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat taught for filthy Lucre, and through Covetouſneſs made Merchandize of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſee 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. &amp;c. and be ſerious in the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof. But I would have them like his Miniſters whom they take upon them to be, <hi>viz.</hi> The Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, who preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed freely, as they had freely receiv'd, and labour'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45394:13"/>to keep the Goſpel without charge; and us'd not their Power, but deny'd themſelves of what they might lawfully have done, that they might cut off occaſion from them that deſir'd it; and to be Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt Jeſus, taking him for their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and Pattern in all things; walking in all Lowlineſs, and Meekneſs, and Gentleneſs, and Patience, as he did: See how the Servant of the Lord is to be quallified, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24. &amp;c. So when they appear thus, we may believe they are the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, and have the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to preach; but not before: I would they might own the Grace of God to teach them, that they may be thus. And they that ſay they are <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrates,</hi> I deſire they may make it appear, by forbearing to perſecute and impriſon him in his Members: What? ſhall <hi>Chriſtians</hi> perſecute <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> If they that are perſecuted are Blarneleſs in the ſight of God, for which they ſuffer, their Perſecutors cannot be ſo, in cauſing them to ſuffer: Let this be conſider'd, as it ought in the Fear of God, by ſuch. It is ſaid in the <hi>Revelations, The Devil ſhall cast ſome of you into Priſon,</hi> ſee <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.10. So it doth concern ſuch to ſee that they do not the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's work herein, leſt Iniquity be laid to their Charge for the ſame; if it went ill with them
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45394:14"/>that did not viſit Chriſt in Priſon, can it go well (think ye) with them that caſts him in? who are guilty herein the Lord forgive them. So the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, if he would not bear the Sword in vain, muſt be a Terror to the Evil-doer, and a Praiſe to them that do Well; for, for this end was he impower'd to Govern by the Lord, and not to do contrary: So, in few words, the Magiſtrate is to rule and govern as he ſhould be rul'd and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by the Lord God, that he may anſwer the end of the Lord therein, by doing that which is right in his ſight; otherwiſe, he provokes the Lord againſt himſelf, who is the Judge of all the Earth, and will do right in the Cauſe of the <hi>Poor,</hi> and in the Cauſe of the <hi>Oppreſſed,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe Ear is open to hear their Cry; and when the meaſure of their Sufferings is fill'd up, then doth his own Arm bring Salvation: So it is by continuing in the Faith and Patience that Victory is obtain'd over the Beaſt, and over his Image, over his Mark, and over the number of his Name. So the Lord keep his Suffering People every where, in believing in him, and patiently to ſubmit unto his holy Will; that thereby we may prevail againſt the Enemy of our Souls, in our ſelves, and in others, in all his Beſetments, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:45394:14"/>
            <p>The Sufferings of the People of God call'd <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Worceſterſhire</hi> have been much, by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and otherwiſe ſometimes, ſome of them for ſome years paſt: And there are ſome in Priſon now, who have ſuffer'd as Priſoners many years: And ſome have ſuffer'd, though not many much loſs of their Goods, and by Impriſonment, ſince the late Act came forth; in all which we can, and do Rejoyce, it being for the Teſtimony of our pure Conſciences, and not for any Evil we have done; an Account of whoſe Sufferings may be given more at large hereafter, if God ſhall make way for the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edward Bourn.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
